Finding Aid for Gwendolyn Midlo Hall papers, 1939-1998
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Gwendolyn Midlo Hall papers 1939-1998, 1968-1995
Hall, Gwendolyn Midlo, 1929-
5.5 linear feet
0110 Aa 2
Professor of history, civil rights activist, scholar of African American history. Family and professional correspondence, newspaper clippings, articles, reviews, and printed material reflecting her political activism, her interest in black history, the case of Robert Williams, and her scholarly interests.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Gwendolyn Midlo Hall (Donor No. 4904 ) in numerous accessions.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open for research.
Gwendolyn Midlo Hall was born Gwendolyn Charmaine Midlo in New Orleans, Louisiana in 1929, in a family of Russian- and Polish-Jewish ancestry. Her father Herman Lazard Midlo was a labor attorney and civil rights attorney, who influenced Hall's thinking. She became active in the civil rights movement at an early age. She helped to organize the New Orleans Youth Council, a militant, interracial, anti-segregation movement in 1945, and was elected to the national Executive Board of the Southern Negro Youth Conference. Between 1947 and 1949 she also attended Newcombe College of Tulane University where she completed majors in European and American History.
Hall's deep commitment to the civil rights movement was visible when she was arrested in 1949 for violating segregation laws. Her family sent her to France from 1949 to 1953 where she learned French and studied classical piano. While in France, Hall married Michael Yuspeh (a piano instructor), with whom she had one child, Leonid "Leo" Yuspeh, born in 1951. In 1955 Yuspeh and Hall separated and later divorced.
From 1953 to 1964, Hall worked closely with Harry Haywood (his legal name was Haywood Hall), an African-American leader and member of the American Communist Party, who wrote on topics related to Marxism, particularly as it related to the civil rights movement and the condition of African-Americans in the United States. Hall married Haywood in 1956. They had two children, Rebecca and Haywood. Harry Haywood died in 1985.
Hall received both her bachelor's degree in History (1962) and master's degree in Latin American History (1963) from the University of the Americas in Mexico City. From there she moved to North Carolina, teaching history to students at the rural and predominantly African-American Elizabeth City State College, but her marriage to Haywood Hall and her revolutionary views made the administration so uneasy that she was fired.
Unable to find employment as a teacher, Hall moved to Detroit in 1965 where she worked as a legal secretary. In 1966, Hall entered the Ph.D. program in history at the University of Michigan. At the University of Michigan she also studied modern Russia, Medieval Islam, and Afro-American Anthropology. During this time, Hall also worked as a research assistant at the Bentley Historical Library, conducting oral history interviews with persons involved in various aspects of the heroin addiction problem. In November 1969 Hall wrote to the Governor of Michigan William Milliken urging him to stop the extradition to North Carolina of Robert F. Williams, civil rights activist and president of the Monroe chapter of NAACP, wanted on kidnapping charges. Williams was arrested and extradited to stand trial in 1975. William Kunstler represented Williams in court, Hall chaired the defense committee. Charges against Williams were dropped almost immediately. In the 1960s-early 1970s Hall published articles on the subject of civil rights and racism in Freedomway, Negro Digest, Black World, and The Black Liberator. In the 1970s Hall corresponded with H. Armand Austan, columnist for the Dayton Black Press. In his columns Austan wrote extensively on the subject of racism, prisons, and conditions of the inmates.
Hall's academic career began in the early 1970s at Rutgers University. During her tenure she wrote a number of important monographs on colonialism and slavery, such as critically acclaimed Social Control in Slave Plantation Societies: a Comparison of St. Domingue and Cuba (1971), Africans in Colonial Louisiana: the Development of Afro- Creole Culture in the Eighteenth Century (1992; this book won nine prizes, including the John Hope Franklin Prize of the American Studies Association), Africans in the Americas: Continuities of Ethnicities and Regions (2001), Slavery and African Ethnicities in the Americas: Restoring the Links (2005), as well as numerous articles and book reviews. Based on colonial documents found in the courthouses of Louisiana, France and Spain, Hall developed and published in 2000 a searchable database of 100,000 descriptions of African slaves transported to Louisiana in the 18th-19th centuries.
In 2010 Hall accepted a position as Professor of History at Michigan State University. In 2012 Hall published a book about her husband Harry Haywood A Black Communist in the Freedom Struggle: the Life of Harry Haywood.
Gwendolyn Midlo Hall's awards and honors include the National Endowment for the Humanities "We the People Fellowship," (2006/2007); the Organization of American Historians Distinguished Service Award (2004); NAACP George Washington Lucas Community Service Award (1997); Guggenheim Fellowship (1996); Hall is the Knight of the Order of Arts and Letters, elected by the National Assembly of France (1997).
The Gwendolyn Midlo Hall Papers, 1939-1998, are comprised of materials documenting the professional and personal life of a historian and civil rights activist. The collection is divided into four series: Personal and Biographical, Academic Career, and Writings.
Subjects:
Hall, Gwendolyn Midlo.; African Americans--Michigan.; Black power.; Civil rights workers--Michigan.; Slavery--Caribbean Area--History.; Slavery--Louisiana.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1961-1970.; Williams, Robert F. (Robert Franklin), 1925-1996.; Women civil rights workers--Michigan.; Women historians.
- Personal and Biographical
  Family correspondence constitutes the bulk of the Personal and Biographical series (1 linear foot, 1939-1997). Family correspondence gives a very intimate view of Hall, her academic, social, intellectual and personal activities, and her writing. The series contains a manuscript copy of Hall's autobiography Notes of a Native New Orleans Daughter in which she describes in detail her childhood and youth experience in New Orleans, racial tension, her political activism, including membership in the Communist Party, her marriage to Harry Haywood, life in Detroit in the mid-1960s, encountering with the Ku Klux Klan in North Carolina, and her academic career. Also included in the series is material related to the Ethel and Herman Midlo International Center for New Orleans Studies at the University of New Orleans in order to support, coordinate, and popularize scholarship about the history, culture, and public policy of the greater New Orleans area. Ethel Midlo was instrumental in establishing the Center.
  - Autobiography Notes of a Native New Orleans Daughter (manuscript) (Box 1)
  - Biographical information (includes photographs) (Box 1)
  - Correspondence (family)
    - Undated and fragmentary (Box 1)
    - 1939-1940 (Box 1)
    - 1945-1947 (Box 1)
    - 1949-1973, 8 folders (Box 1)
    - 1985-1991 (Box 1)
    - 1992-1994, 1996-1997 (Box 1)
  - Ethel and Herman Midlo International Center for New Orleans Studies (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Activism
  The Activism series (0.5 linear feet, 1969-1987) contains Hall's correspondence with columnist H. Armand Austan and clippings and drafts of Austan's articles; correspondence with Michigan Governor Milliken regarding extradition of Robert F. Williams dated 1969 and 1972; also addresses, tributes, events programs, and correspondence between Hall and the Williams family after Robert Williams' death in 1996. Also found here are Hall's FOIA requests for CIA and other government files about Hall, and collected articles and clippings. The Harry Haywood folder contains issues of Soulbook with articles by Haywood.
  - Collected newspaper articles (Box 2)
  - Freedom of Information request 1987 (Box 2)
  - H. Armand Austan (correspondence)
    - 1972-1973, 6 folders (Box 2)
    - 1974, 1977-1978 (scattered) (Box 2)
    - Newspaper clippings, writings (Box 2)
  - Harry Haywood (Box 2)
  - Robert F. Williams
    - 1969, 1971 (Box 2)
    - 1996-1998 (Box 2)
- Academic Career
  Materials comprising Hall's Academic Career series (2.5 linear feet, 1963-1998) focus on her teaching and research. The details surrounding her dismissal from the Elizabeth City State College in North Carolina reflect the racial tension of the 1960s. Later papers include correspondence with colleagues at Rutgers University, grant and research proposals that Hall initiated, conferences in which she participated (including the 1986 Conference on Nicaraguan Constitution), and lectures. Professional correspondence mainly contains letters from various historians and publishers. Filed chronologically are not only incoming letters, but copies of Hall's outgoing letters as well.
  - Awards (Box 2)
  - Conferences
    - 1971, 1996 (Box 2)
    - Nicaraguan National Constitution 1986 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence
    - Undated and fragmentary (Box 2)
    - 1963-1965, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - 1966-1973, 7 folders (Box 3)
    - 1977-1982 (Box 3)
    - 1984-1995, 15 folders (Box 3)
    - 1996-1998, 3 folders (Box 4)
    - Regarding publications 1988-1993 (Box 4)
  - Lectures
    - 1991-1994 (Box 4)
    - Congo Square Lectures November 5, 1988 (VHS tape) (Box 4)
    - Burkina Faso 1987 (Box 4)
  - Elizabeth City State College, NC 1964-1966 (Box 4)
  - Research files, 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Research and grant proposals and reports 1970s-1990s, 4 folders (Box 4)
  - Rutgers University 1971-1991 (Box 4)
- Writings
  Samples of Hall's Writings (1 linear foot, 1963-1995) include her early works, such as her 1963 Master's Thesis titled Negro Slavery in Brazil, her stage and screen plays adapted from her book The Creole Slaves of Louisiana: Roots of the Afro-Latin Heritage of the United States, a 1964 draft of an unpublished novel titled Angry Young Man, and various essays and drafts. The series includes manuscript essays and articles organized by subject and printed articles organized in alphabetical order by name of publication in which they appeared. Of interest are writings on the subject of drug use and drug trafficking in Detroit, race and racism, issues of urban African Americans, and education for African Americans. Included in the series her book Africans in Colonial Louisiana and a copy of Love, War, and the 96th Engineers (Colored) edited by Hall. Also book reviews, both by Hall and about her works.
  - Africans in Colonial Louisiana, 1992 (advance uncorrected proofs) (Box 5)
  - Angry Young Man, 1964-1965 (novel) (Box 5)
  - Black Resistance and White Repression (book chapter draft) (Box 5)
  - Creole Slaves in Louisiana, undated (screenplay) (Box 5)
  - Devil in the Caribbean: the Spanish, the French, and the Carib Indians (Box 5)
  - Formation of Afro-Creole Culture (Box 5)
  - Man, 1964-1965 (play) (Box 5)
  - Negro Slavery in Brazil, 1963 (Master's Thesis) (Box 5)
  - Proposal for an Oral History Project in Urban and Black History (draft) (Box 5)
  - Slave Power: the Creole in Louisiana (screenplay), 1985 (Box 5)
  - Social Control in Slave Plantation Societies, 1970 (Doctoral Dissertation) (Box 5)
  - Youth Rebellion and Black Revolution, 1967 (Box 5)
  - Untitled thesis December 1963 (draft) (Box 5)
  - Essays (manuscript)
    - Colonialism and slavery (Box 5)
    - Drug use and trafficking (Box 5)
    - Education (Box 5)
    - Human rights in China (Box 5)
    - Notes (various) (Box 5)
    - Race and racism, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Urban issues (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 5)
  - Articles published in journals (Box 6)
    - Aché, 1990 (Box 6)
    - Chicory Review, 1988-1989 (Box 6)
    - Negro Digest, 1968-1970 (Box 6)
    - Various articles (Box 6)
  - Books
    - Africans in Colonial Louisiana, 1992 (Box 6)
    - Love, War, and the 96th Engineers (Colored) (edited), 1995 (Box 6)
  - Book reviews
    - By Hall (Box 6)
    - Of Hall's work (Box 6)
Related Material
More material concerning Hall can be found at the Gwendolyn Midlo Hall Collection at the Amistad Research Center at Tulane University and the Herman L. Midlo Collection at the Earl K. Long Library of the University of New Orleans.